Register of the Vlastimil Kybal Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1913-1957 (Box 5)
  - "The European War and Its Ideological Background," 1939 December 5. (Folder 16: 3-4)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes some clippings
  - "The New Central Europe," 17th session of the Institute of World Affairs, 1939 December 13. (Folder 16: 5-6)
    Typescript. Includes some correspondence, clippings, and round-table bibliographies and agendas
  - "No War but a Greater Germany Is Coming: Comment by a European Diplomat," 1940? (Folder 16: 7)
    Background material, typescript, and correspondence
  - Review of Boris Souvarine, Stalin: A Critical Survey of Bolshevism, 1940? (Folder 17: 1)
  - Review of Duncan Aikman, The All-American Front, 1940? (Folder 17: 2)
  - Review of T. Geoffrey Garratt, What Has Happened to Europe?, 1940? (Folder 17: 3)
  - "Stalin," 1940? (Folder 17: 4)
  - "Economic Posibilities in Latin America," 1940. (Folder 17: 5)
  - "The Creative Work of the Czech Nation," lecture, University of California, Los Angeles, 1940 January 12. (Folder 17: 6)
  - "Stalin's Hard Days Have Begun," 1940 February 14. (Folder 17: 7)
  - Review of W. G. Krivitsky, "In Stalin's Secret Service," 1940 February 17. (Folder 17: 8)
  - "Masaryk a ceskoslovenska samostatnost," speech, Thomas G. Masaryk Society of Los Angeles, 1940 March 2. (Folder 17: 9)
  - "Masaryk a Nemci," speech, Ceskoslovenska Beseda, Pasadena, California, 1940 March 7. (Folder 17: 10)
  - "Masaryk's Ideas of Democracy and a New Europe," lecture, Athenaeum, Pasadena, California, 1940 April 18. (Folder 17: 11)
  - "Masaryk about Slavs," lecture, Athenaeum, Pasadena, California, 1940 April 18. (Folder 17: 12)
  - "Masaryk's Work of Liberation," lecture, Athenaeum, Pasadena, California, 1940 April 18. (Folder 17: 13)
  - "The Succession States of Austria-Hungary," lecture, California Institute of Technology, 1940 May 20. (Folder 17: 14)
  - "Latin America's Place in World Politics," lecture, Whittier Institute of International Relations, California, 1940 June 28 (also delivered at California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, 1941) (Folder 17: 15-16)
  - "The Central European Problem," lecture, University of California, Los Angeles, 1940 July 29. (Folder 17: 17)
  - "The New Economic Order in Central Europe," lecture, University of California, Los Angeles, 1940 July 29. (Folder 17: 18)
  - "The Changing Social Structure of the Latin-American Countries," University of California, Los Angeles, 1940 August 1. (Folder 17: 19)
  - "Cultural Relations between Czechoslovakia and the Spanish and Portuguese Speaking Countries," speech, University of California, Los Angeles, 1940 August 14. (Folder 17: 20)
  - Review of Otto D. Tolischus, They Wanted War, 1940 September? (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - "The Future of Central Europe," The First Congregational Church of Los Angeles, 1940 September 1. (Folder 18: 2)
  - "The New Central Europe," 1940 October 3. (Folder 18: 3)
  - "Culture and Education in Latin America," lecture, Pasadena Junior College, 1940 October 22. (Folder 18: 4)
  - "Situace v Evrope a zvlaste v Ceskoslovensku," Ceskoslovenska Beseda, Pasadena, California, 1940 November 7. (Folder 18: 5)
  - "The Czech Question," 1940 December 1. (Folder 18: 6)
  - "South America's Place in World Economy," World Affairs Interpreter, 1940 Winter. (Folder 18: 7)
  - Reading notes to William Edward Dodd, Ambassador Dodd's Diary, 1933-1938, 1941? (Folder 18: 8-9)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes a printed copy of the diary
  - "American Pledge for Czechoslovak Independence," 1941. (Folder 18: 10)
  - "The Anti-Nazi Europe," 1941. (Folder 18: 11)
  - "Checoslovaquia: Su opresion y su resurreccion," 1941. (Folder 18: 12-13)
    Typescript. Includes some correspondence
  - "Checoslovaquia: Su opresion y su resurreccion," 1941. (Box-folder 19: 1-3)
  - "Czech Revolt not Directed by Moscow," 1941. (Folder 19: 4)
  - "The Governments-In-Exile: The United Nations of the Subjugated Europe," lecture, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, 1941. (Folder 19: 5)
  - "Hess's Affair," 1941. (Folder 19: 6)
  - "K otazce uznani Ceskoslovenska," 1941. (Folder 19: 7)
  - Karel Havlicek a nase svoboda, Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni, Chicago, 1941. (Folder 19: 8)
    Holograph, typescript, and printed copy (in Czech)
  - "Mexico," lecture, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, 1941. (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - Note on "Czechoslovak War Aims," Benes' exclusive interview with the Chicago Daily News, 1941. (Folder 20: 2)
  - Note on "The New Europe," Benes' statement to the Vrij Neederland, 1941. (Folder 20: 3)
  - "Pomahejme Americe," 1941. (Folder 20: 4)
  - "The Problem of the Small European Nations," lecture, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, 1941. (Folder 20: 5)
  - Review of Arnold Wolfers, Britain and France between Two Wars: Conflicting Strategies of Peace since Versailles, 1941. (Folder 20: 6)
  - Review of Svetislav-Sveta Petrovitch, Free Yugoslavia Calling, 1941. (Folder 20: 7)
  - Review of Jules Romains, Seven Mysteries of Europe, 1941 February 7. (Folder 20: 8)
  - Review of Maurice Hindus, To Sing with the Angels, 1941 February 24. (Folder 20: 9)
  - "Masaryk," speech, Ceskoslovenska Beseda, Pasadena, California, 1941 March 6. (Folder 20: 10)
  - "Economic Relations between the United States and Latin America," 1941 April 1. (Folder 20: 11)
  - "Czechoslovak Youth Starving in France," 1941 April 21. (Folder 20: 12)
  - Speech on the role of the Czech nation in the fight against Nazism, La Crescenta, California, 1941 April 27. (Folder 20: 13)
  - "Prague: A City of Art," Women's Club of South Pasadena, California, 1941 May 14. (Folder 20: 14)
  - "John Hus," 1941 July 6. (Folder 20: 15-19)
    Research notes and typescript (in English and Czech)
  - "Husitske dedictvi: Jan Hus a jeho vyznam pro dnesni zapas," New-Yorske Listy, 1941 July 6. (Box-folder 21: 1)
    Holograph, typescript, and printed copy (in Czech). Includes typescript in English
  - Letter to the editor, The Times, 1941 July 22. (Folder 21: 2)
  - "Popravy u nas," Ceskoslovenska Beseda, Pasadena, California, 1941 October 2. (Folder 21: 3)
  - "Latin America's Place in World Economics," lecture, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, 1941 November 14. (Folder 21: 4)
  - "Masarykuv pocit vecnosti," 1942? (Folder 21: 5)
  - Review of Stoyan Pribichevich, World without End: The Saga of Southeastern Europe, 1942? (Folder 21: 6)
  - "The Case against Habsburg Restoration," 1942. (Folder 21: 7)
  - "Churchill and the World Struggle Against Nazism," 1942. (Folder 21: 8-12)
    Research notes and typescript (in Czech and English)
  - "Economic Problems of the Planned Central Europe," 1942. (Folder 21: 13)
  - "Lidice," 1942. (Folder 21: 14)
  - "Odnemceni," 1942. (Folder 21: 15)
  - "The Old and New Europe," 1942. (Folder 21: 16)
  - Review of Otto Habsburg, Danubian Reconstruction, 1942. (Folder 21: 17)
  - "The Czechoslovak Unit of the American Red Cross," 1942 January 14. (Folder 21: 18)
  - "Economic Inter-American Cooperation During the War Emergency," California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, 1942 January 23. (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - "Masaryk a pangermanism," Svornost, 1942 March 2. (Folder 22: 2)
    Typescript and printed copy (in Czech)
  - Note on the Pan-American Conference at Rio de Janeiro, 1942 March 5. (Folder 22: 3)
  - "Pozdrav do vlasti," radio address, 1942 March 7. (Folder 22: 4)
    Holograph and typescript (in Czech)
  - "Masaryk a ceskoslovensky stat," 1942 March 8. (Folder 22: 5)
  - "Komensky a nas zapas," New-Yorske Listy, 1942 March 29. (Folder 22: 6)
  - "Comenius," speech, Czechoslovak Unit of the American Red Cross, Pasadena, California, 1942 April 10. (Folder 22: 7)
  - "Pomozme Prazske Universite," Svornost, 1942 June 9. (Folder 22: 8)
  - "O teroru v Cechach a na Morave," Ceskoslovenska Beseda, Pasadena, California, 1942 July 4. (Folder 22: 9)
  - "The Problems of the Armistice," speech, United Nations Committee of Southern California, 1942 October 14. (Folder 22: 10)
  - "Czechoslovak Independence Day," letter to the editor, Los Angeles Times, 1942 October 29. (Folder 22: 11)
  - "K situaci v Cechach," Ceskoslovenska Beseda, Pasadena, California, 1942 November 5. (Folder 22: 12)
  - "The Atlantic Charter," World Affairs Interpreter, 1942 Winter. (Folder 22: 13-16)
    Notes, typescript, printed copy, and clippings
  - "Masaryk a druhy odboj," speech, Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni, Los Angeles, 1943 April 18. (Box-folder 23: 1)
  - Speech on the Czechoslovak position in Europe, Studen Church, Occidental College, Los Angeles, 1943 September 12. (Folder 23: 2)
  - "The Slavs and the Germans," Occidental College, Los Angeles, 1943 September 27. (Folder 23: 3)
  - "Marx vs. Palacky," 1944. (Folder 23: 4)
    Research notes and typescript (in Czech)
  - "Masaryk," radio broadcast, WSUI Radio Station, Iowa City, 1944 March 7. (Folder 23: 5)
  - "Masaryk's Religious Philosophy," First Unitarian Church, Iowa City, 1944 March 19. (Folder 23: 6)
  - "Masaryk's Message," speech, Masaryk Celebration, Cedar Rapids, Iowa, 1944 March 26. (Folder 23: 7)
  - "The Atlantic Charter," radio broadcast, WSUI Radio Station, Iowa City, 1944 April 7. (Folder 23: 8)
  - "The Restoration of Czechoslovakia," 1944 April 21. (Folder 23: 9)
  - Speech, Czech colony, Iowa City, 1944 April 23. (Folder 23: 10)
  - "Our Duties," radio broadcast, WHFC Radio Station, Chicago, 1944 April 30. (Folder 23: 11)
  - "Chair of American Civilization at Charles University of Prague," 1944 June. (Folder 23: 12)
    Typescript and correspondence with different American universities regarding the founding of the International University in Prague
  - "Franklin D. Roosevelt: A Biography," 1948. (Folder 23: 13-17)
    Typescript (incomplete). Includes footnotes, table of contents, research notes, and some correspondence
  - Organisace spojenych narodu, Prague, 1948. (Box-folder 24: 1)
  - "Za nasi svobodu v Americe," 1949?
    - Part 1, Vzpominky z Kalifornie, 1939-1943 (Folder 24: 2)
    - Table of contents of Part 2, Historicko-politicke uvahy z let valecnych, 1939-1945 (Folder 24: 3)
  - "Franklin D. Roosevelt: Zivotopis," New-Yorske Listy, 1949 March 27 - November 27 (in Czech)
    - Typescript. (Folder 24: 4-8)
      Includes footnotes, table of contents, research notes and bibliography
    - Typescript. (Box-folder 25: 1-7)
    - Printed copy (Folder 25: 8-9)
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 26: 1-2)
  - "Czechoslovakia: Present and Future," 1950 January 5. (Folder 26: 3)
  - Speech on the political situation in Europe, First Presbytarian Church, Orlando, Florida, 1950 January 22. (Folder 26: 4)
  - Speech to Rotarians, Hermosillo, Mexico, 1951 January 21. (Folder 26: 5)
  - "Politicky listar Alese Hrdlicky: 1916-1943," 1952? (Folder 26: 6)
    Typescript (in Czech and English)
  - "Ales Hrdlicka jako politik a vlastenec," Svornost, 1952 July 27. (Folder 26: 7)
    Printed copy (in Czech). Includes excerpts from Hrdlicka's correspondence deposited in the Smithonian Institution, and two biographical memoirs of Hrdlicka (in English and Czech)
  - Speech on communism in Czechoslovakia, Pennsylvania Club, Orlando, Florida, 1955 April 15. (Folder 26: 8)
  - "Today's Message of St. Francis of Assisi," speech, The Knights of Columbus, Orlando, Florida, 1955 April 18. (Folder 26: 9)
  - "Americane a Cechy r. 1945," 1956 October 9. (Folder 26: 10)
  - "Hrobari republiky," Denni Hlasatel, 1956 December 1. (Folder 26: 11)
  - "To the Quakers in Orlando," 1957 February 24. (Folder 26: 12)
- ACADEMIC CAREER FILE, 1943-1944. (Box 27)
  Course material for lectures given at Iowa University
  - Czech literature and history (Folder 27: 1)
  - Italy (Folder 27: 2-6)
- SLAVIC CULTURAL ASSOCIATION, 1942-1943
  - Agreement (Folder 27: 7)
  - Correspondence (Folder 27: 8)
  - Transcripts of broadcasts by Kybal, Slavic Radio Program, KPAS, 1942-1943 (Folder 27: 9-10)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1957 (Box 28)
  - Tito, Josip Broz. (Folder 28: 1)
    Includes a typewritten memorandum and cover letter, dated 1957 January 29, on Tito's prospective visit to the United States, compiled by Kybal at the request of Mgr. Bishop
  - United Nations (Folder 28: 2)
  - United States. Office of War Information. War Crimes and Damages Group (Folder 28: 3)
  - World War, 1914-1918 (Folder 28: 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 28: 5)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1938-1966. (Box-folder 29: 1-5)